Knowledge is power.
>> Reality is
[music]
have a question that I want to start
with. I was listening to you um I
believe it was one of your TED talks and
uh where I would like to start if it's
okay with you. You said most of us carry
unconscious vocal habits that interfere
with us doing our best work. What do you
mean by that?
>> Well, I'll I'll make a ridiculous
example to start with. So, if the first
words out of my mouth sounded like this,
you know, you might have a different
sense of who I might be. Or [snorts] if
I was talking like this or like this.
So, those are extreme examples.
However,
most of us are using our kind of
unconscious default voice that we think
is us, but it's not. It's cobbled
together with duct tape and popsicle
sticks and trauma and habit and
something somebody said to us when we
were five and just our story about who
we are. And it's the story is always too
small.
So I like to bring awareness and choice
into how people express themselves
because you know the only thing we have
is anything that happens in the world
happens because we talk about it. A
relationship, a business, a podcast, a
book, uh family, anything. So
>> that's what I mean by that.
>> Yeah. Great. Brilliant. Um okay. So how
in which ways do I think you mentioned
trauma as one of the things in which
ways do our earlier experiences in life
let's say especially maybe childhood
teenage years how do that how does that
shape our voice long term
>> oh so many ways I go through a lot of
tissue when I'm teaching in person
>> I imagine yeah [laughter]
>> because you open up the voice and the
truth comes out so a lot of us get the
truth in our guts you know we have this
wisdom this knowing we have whole
another brain in our guts Now we know
grandma knew that. The language tells us
about gut instinct but um and so the
truth rises up and then if you can't say
what's so and most of us can't um it
gets stuck in our throat and so there's
a a cut there and then there's also just
a cut culturally between the body and
the head. The head is favored. the body
is like second
fiddle. Although it's getting better.
There's sematic therapies now and
there's like more embodiment practices
than than there have been. But still
most of us walk around with our body
being kind of a little stock to carry
our brain around. And um so
a lot of my clients have been the
keepers of secrets in their family.
A lot of them had somebody say some
horrible [laughter]
thing to them. Sometimes it was like a
music teacher when they were in third
grade. I don't know where these people
come from and they should not be near
our children.
>> Like, you know, you can't sing, move
your lips. Um
uh and then there's just cultural
pileon. You know, what it means to be a
man, what it means to be a woman, what
it means to be a good person usually
doesn't involve being primal,
loud, hysterical, uh, playful. It gets
very narrow, our voices. And so, we're
all kind of wearing a a vocal girdle,
>> right?
>> For lack of a better. And then so and
then so you work with people like what
are what are some of the ways that not
only how you identify like where you can
help people point out like hey you see
how your voice is doing that or you
identify I think you have your five
different elements that you sort them
into. So do you point those out to
people and then what are your steps to
kind of release those things to free up
their voice?
>> Well
we start big. We start beyond speaking
and singing in sound because that sets
us that's like the dog bark for your
voice. You know, you just take it off
the leash and swat it on the butt and
send it off to play. Love it.
>> And so we start with sound because that
was what liberated me. I had a lot of I
had a lot of good singing in my life as
a young person. I was really great
grateful to be in good choirs.
Uh, but I never wanted to sing alone
ever in front of anyone, which is a
common fear except that my grandfather,
my mother, and my brother were all
accomplished solo singers. And so that
lovely question, what's wrong with me?
Uh, showed up because I would I felt
like I I would die if I tried to do
that. So, I ended up going to a VO voice
workshop in Minneapolis in my late 20s,
a long time ago. And when I walked in, I
thought, "My voice ended here." And What
was beyond that sound was nothing. No
sound. And that was my story. That's the
truth I lived in. And in that first
workshop,
I made sound all the way up here. I
don't know if you can hear that, but
it's almost to the top of the piano. And
it wasn't singing anymore. And I wasn't
me anymore. I was a character, which is
another thing I do with people is to
pretend to be somebody else. Because
then you'll do something that quote
unquote you would never do. only guess
what that's you two. So this this
distance set me, you know, blew that
story apart and set me on this path that
I'm still traveling. So we start with
sound. We pretend to be characters and
then I isolate and exaggerate each of
the five elements to sort of give people
a sense of what's the full range of
possibility. So, the elements are earth
and that's you.
[laughter] You're an earth guy.
>> Not surprising. We'll come back to that.
>> Earth, fire,
water,
metal, and air.
>> Each one sounds different. Each one is
connected to a different part of the
body and each one is useful for certain
things and terrible for other things. So
we generally go through the five
elements sort of assessing
who's home, who's missing and what
mostly what people are noticing you know
in their body, mind, memory,
imagination.
So,
>> okay. And then in that moment, I was
thinking about this as I was writing
down some notes. In that moment when
they notice it, because I think um you
know, when when we're singing in unison,
for example, if we kind of become aware
of just our own voice, you kind of have
this instant reaction of like I'm maybe
singing off key or I have this, you
know, whatever. How do you get past that
initial that first big barrier? It's got
to be a big wall, right? at first when
we first initially hear our voice and we
want to like shut down and kind of get
rid of it.
>> You know, there are people who said,
"I've been working on getting to your
studio for three years." [laughter]
I first heard about you. So, I think a
lot of the work happens before they like
sign up for an online coaching session
or a class or or something because it is
crazy. Why do people come? Why do people
do this? It is terrifying. I'm I'm over
my fear now, but I still really remember
that breathless
terror that showed up. So, I do think
pretending to be somebody else is kind
of secret sauce,
>> you know, because the ego means well,
right? It's like trying to protect us,
but it's way too small. So
just pretending for a minute to be drunk
Julia child,
you know, or or a pissed-off cat or ah
little baby or something. It it uh it's
playful. So, I think making it fun,
playful, and I usually occupy the most
ridiculous place in the room so that
everybody else can just relax a little
bit more cuz, you know, I am a lunatic.
>> Yeah. Well, yeah. You give permission to
to other people, you know, they they can
open that door because they've seen you
open it. Uh it it makes me think of uh
one of my favorite people in the world.
He was my theater teacher in high
school. I've actually had him on the
podcast luckily. Um, and so he talked
about that too. His name was David Craig
and he would talk about he would always
be the inspiration. Um, his his subtext
of life was dare to be different. Um, he
would always wear costumes. He would
always just try to be the one to kind of
shake the the typical way we see the
world. Um, and and on the podcast,
that's what I was kind of asking him.
Uh, just kind of how how he saw the
world, how he interfaced with it, and he
had a mentor that taught him.
Essentially, he was like, I noticed that
there was this character as well of
David Craig, and I could feed into it. I
could be the character of David Craig,
of Mr. Craig, the teacher. And that
helped him kind of even step out of what
he was naturally or, you know, maybe any
insecurities or whatever he may have.
Um, and play the character of this
teacher that everybody thought was
exuberant and playful and and all of
these things. Um, and man, that has
stuck with me since our conversation,
since he taught me in high school, for
sure. Since our conversation, I think
about that so often. Playing the the
character of this thing can really uh
break us out of who we typically have
been.
>> Yeah. And the I was a theater kid also
saved my life actually. And uh people
were saying what are you going to do
with a theater degree? And it's like
well watch you know two books
>> treating people all over the world you
know and part of it is just learning to
loosen the bonds of who I think I am but
part of what informed this work uh the
five elements framework was also yian
psychology and the idea of archetypes
you know there are these uh forms you
know energy forms that are like the king
the warrior the princess the airhead
head, the fool, the high priestess, all
you know, all these characters. And I
think our ancestors made really good use
of them,
>> right? They were always like invoking
the unseen world. And we do that in this
work as well. And it's powerful. I I
couldn't make the sounds I made. I was a
bird at the time. [laughter]
Only now that bird is part of Barbara,
>> right? I couldn't go back into the same
shape. Now I am Burn.
[laughter] I'm sorry.
>> I'll be one of those irritating people
who changes her name.
>> Um, and so, uh, I include, you know,
that archetypal, it's a I think it's a
sacred invocation of the unseen. And I
think they just want to help us. I think
they're looking for jobs, you know,
there's like, you got anything for me?
Because there is this feeling. I think
most artists have had this, you know,
actors or writers or singers where you
feel something rising up in you that is
more than you.
>> And oh my gosh, I live for that.
>> Oh yeah.
>> So I do feel like the characters, you
know, you can do these big archetypes,
but I also think about real people, you
know, I have uh I often invoke Maya
Angelou when I want to slow down. I'm
6'2. I'm a very tall person and so is
she. And when I want to slow down and
inhabit my warm dignity and gravitas, I
call in Maya Angelou and she changes me,
right? And so you have one too in your
your theater teacher, you know that um
that boldness. And so whenever I'm
presenting or teaching, I'm the high
priestess and the holy fool. That helps
me know that I'm doing sacred work, but
not to take it too seriously. And I
think about Maya Angelou and my friend
Margaret Wheatley who's the leadership
author, world famous human being uh who
I did a lot of work with in over the
years and she has a very clear and
deliberate way of speaking and so she
helps me be more clear. So I have my
little cadre with me when I'm whenever
I'm teaching or speaking and
>> yeah the gang's all here. I I
>> [laughter]
>> such elegance um as you as you're just
presenting them to me, as you're kind of
slipping through them. Um obviously that
is where we want to get where we have
these different archetypes within us and
and based off of the specific moment we
allow them to kind of take the reign so
to say. um
when we're learning um I'm always
fascinated with um Tony Robbins talks
about priming a lot like he gets himself
before he gets into one of his events or
went to the one of these business
situation he gets himself into the right
state before he goes into it. Um is this
something that you teach or is this was
this part of your path where you would
go okay I need to be like my aunt before
I walk in into here or I need to embody
this person before I walk into this
building. Was that part of your process
at all?
>> Well, I do feel like uh
I like to make great big changes before
I make small ones. So, I wanted
everybody into the pool first, right?
The gang. I wanted more of the gang
before I got too
I think a lot of times, especially
culturally, we're always trying to get
to the the point. We're trying to like
go fast and narrow and I want to open
first. So that feels like liberation to
get out of the the voice box that we've
all been living in. And so
uh
I I want to I I have my my students do a
lot of the warming up with the five
elements, exploring them. It's kind of
like a yoga practice only for your
voice. It's like the full range of
motion with awareness. And just get used
to inhabiting all these different sounds
in a big and small way. And usually the
voice, unless it's been hurt in some
way, you know, damaged physically, the
voice is usually much more ready to go
than the psyche.
>> Like the voice is like even if it's
been, you know, deep trauma. I've worked
with people who've been through awful
things, but usually the voice is just
like, "Yes, let's go." You know,
[laughter]
but the psyche is like, "No, wait. I'm
an introvert."
>> Or in my case, I hated what I, you know,
what I call the air voice. This high,
soft, sweet voice. It's like, "Oh, for
God's sake, I'm from Minnesota. I'm
tall. I'm smart." You know, I could
never get away with the little, "Hi, I'm
just like, it grossed me out." And
like most people, the parts of my voice
I hate the most or I feel most
uncomfortable with have the greatest
gifts for me
>> because it represents a part of us
that's in exile somehow. And so for me,
I didn't think that ear voice belonged
to me partly because of social norms. I
was like I couldn't fit the social norm.
But deeper
I like everyone rushed out of childhood
really quickly. had to grow up really
fast. And this is how we sound when
we're when we're little. So I had when I
opened up all that voice, there was just
so many tears. So much healing of little
Barbara, you know, little Barbie who
didn't feel like she could, you know, be
her civil sweet self. And now when that
voice came back over time, it brought a
lot of gifts like a a diff a lightness.
You know, I used to hang out down here
because being a fake boy was a good
thing in my family.
>> My dad didn't like women very much. And
we're good. He died. All is well.
>> We we got we got to a good place before
he died.
But he was kind of an ass and and
sarcastic. And so I just kind of um as
the only girl, you know, in the family,
I was like, I'm going to be a fake boy.
>> Strategy. And so when this came back,
oh, this lightness came back. I changed
the way I walk, uh, changed the way I
dress, changed the way I speak and sing,
but mostly it just like popped open a
different kind of spiritual connection
to the sacred feminine.
>> Wow. Brilliant. Okay. Um, yeah. I I
really like I feel like you're painting
the picture of, you know, uh this,
you know, let's just say broadly our ego
kind of being like a cork in some ways
of of uh like just all these different
versions of our fluency that that could
be coming out. Um makes me think of uh
Allan Watts, I think it was, who said
the ego is uh a great servant but a
terrible master. Exactly.
>> And um so it seems to be I do love often
talking about identity on this podcast.
How does our identity, our ego, who we
think ourselves to be now, how does that
get in the way of our true voice
expressing
>> in every way. And you know, I used to
hate the ego. I used to get all up in
my, you know, grumpiness about the ego.
It's like, ah, such a pain. You know,
it's always interfering with my freedom.
And now I'm just like, oh honey, thank
you.
>> Mhm. Right. It's like it is like I think
of it as like a a a pet like a dog who
doesn't know the difference between the
postal carrier and an intruder. And it
means well it wants to protect me. And
it does. It keeps me anchored in a
story.
And bless its heart. It's got a
function.
And like a dog, it can be trained. It's
like, "Honey, I'm gonna leave who you
think Barbara is right now, but I'll be
back. So, sit, stay." Uh, and so,
actually, one of the songs I wrote about
this is called Brain Rats. It goes, I'm
going to sing you a little bit of it. It
goes like this, and it's just about
that's going to happen no matter what
whenever we step outside of who we think
we are. So, here's the here's the
chorus, and I'll send you the link to
the uh YouTube video because funny.
>> Brain [singing] rats. [music] I've got
brain rats,
a pestilential blight upon my mind.
[singing]
Brain rats are those wicked thoughts
that [music] prove my every [singing]
flaw. And every hopeful notion gives
them something new to
I hear them chewing [singing] in the
night and on and off all day. They've
really got [music] my number. All the
awful stuff they say. [singing]
And then off we go to just other verses.
But I feel like the brain rats are the
ego
trying to protect us.
>> And the stretch outside of that
container needs to be gradual like yoga.
You know, you stretch outside and say,
"Okay, I'm going to be a little less
introverted or a little more a little
lighter." But you don't do it all at
once. Most people it's a negotiation.
It's like, "Okay, we're going to go out
a little. Okay, now we have to come back
in a little bit. Now we're going to go
out a little bit. Oh, that's an edge.
Okay, we'll come right back in again.
>> Okay. Yeah. And and
yoga is defined it's it's yoke, union,
union with self. Um,
how do we, you know, as people are going
through this, I'm sure they come up with
things that they need to,
you know, keep, accept, but also get rid
of. Um, how do you how do you kind of
divvy that up? You know, when uh
>> I I I just imagine some of these
conversations that you have with people
as they're freeing up their voice could
probably be incredibly overwhelming. You
know, suddenly they're they're like,
"Oh, I just wanted to sing and now I
need to process this like pretty pretty
heavy heavy thing, you know." Um, I
don't know. I guess uh what does that
seem to look like? What what have you
experienced in that in in that realm?
Like as people are um you know
uncovering things that maybe they didn't
plan on uncovering and then trying to
figure out what to get rid of and what
what to also unify.
>> Well, yeah. Uh I only take people where
they want to go, but I've gotten more
accurate about sending, you know,
sending the little bleep bleep out into
the world. Usually people are who are
finding me are interested in
transformation.
However, I have I mean I was an
organizational development consultant
for 12 years. So I was in the world of
business. No training in that whatsoever
but very useful
>> in working with lots of leaders, teams,
people in the workplace. And so and I'm
from Minnesota so it has to be
practical. So this work can be really
strategic and practical to say, okay, if
you're a leader and you have to give a
speech, you probably are going to need
to use your fire voice. I I did a a
video uh when I did some work with a guy
who did a video who was talking about
being really passionate about his work
and you know he was horrified. He was
passionate, but he was an introverted
white guy from North Dakota. So, his
idea of passion was like he was having a
party inside, but nobodyated. We can't
tell.
>> Yeah, he's elated, but he looks like
he's in a coma. And so, uh, we worked
with him to help add fire to what he how
he was speaking in that situation and
also when he was doing presentations.
And he had it. He found it. We just
needed to sort of and it's always like
tricky with introverts. I'm right in the
middle so I'm a lot of both. Um it's
always going to feel like a second
language, you know, full expression to
introverts. But hey, there's a lot of
people living really well in second and
third languages. So,
you know, it can be very practical
about, you know, how you talk in a
presentation versus if you have really
bad news to deliver. you know, I'm so
sorry we have to let you go feels very
different in the water voice than I'm
really sorry we have to let you go.
Right? So, it can be very pragmatic and
strategic if people want to enter that
way. But here's the thing is no matter
where they enter, the rest of it's
waiting for them because you can't
change your voice without having your
life come along for the ride. So,
wherever people enter, it can be around
speaking or singing or just feeling like
they want to be more free, freely
expressed in their life.
>> Um, wherever they enter, pragmatic or
transformational,
it's all sitting right there.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Wait, waiting to unpack. Um,
okay. Uh, tell me more about your
initial beginning on this journey. Uh, I
think I heard I think you mentioned that
you had a mentor that inspired you down
down this path. What did that look like?
>> Oh yeah. Uh the guy who took me on that
that first journey, his name is Shaul
Ryan. He's a teacher with the Roy Heart
Center in the south of France. He's a
British guy with a Hebrew name who lives
in France. Um but he was my teacher. He
was so I was so scared in that first
weekend. And he was he's this kind,
calm, playful, gentle man. and um
I felt safe enough to try things in his
presence and then uh he directed me. I
fell in love with this work instantly
and I got a grant and went to the south
of France and studied with a couple of
other teachers that he recommended and
then also followed this other person
Richard Armstrong who's the teacher more
of a singer uh teacher you know
Richard's more of a singer Sha was more
of an actor and so I worked with Richard
both in France and in Canada and then
years went by I kept working with Sha
and his partner Carol when they would
come to the Twin Cities and And I don't
even remember uh when, but he reached
out and said, "Hey, I'm coming. Would
you like to teach together?" I was like,
"Uh me?" So, I guess I was worthless the
first year because I [laughter] was so
freaked out. Just like come on, you got
anything? [laughter]
>> Like, oh my god. Oh my god. And then um
then I got over it and we taught
together for over 20 years uh co-led uh
workshops and then just last year he
said I'm 80 I'm not going to make the
trip now.
>> Yeah.
>> And so the joy of it is that my nephew
Travis
uh who lives in Atlanta has been
studying with Shaul and me for many many
years and has trained in my work. I've
trained about 75 people in to be
trainers or coaches in this approach.
And he um he and I are now teaching
together. We did our first one last fall
and we have another one in a couple of
weeks.
>> Um
and you know, we're
innovating [clears throat]
because we're the next generation. So,
>> taking what we've learned and then he's
done a lot of circle singing, vocal
improv. He's an amazing singer and
teacher. He'll He's a better teacher
than I'll I'll be. You know what I mean?
It's like
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> That's That's what's supposed to happen.
>> Beautiful. Yeah.
>> I have somebody in my family like
>> Yeah. That must be fantastic to say the
least. What um what are you learning
from your nephew? What what has he
taught you? What have you learned from
him?
>> Well, he has studied with uh Rian who
does a lot of vocal improvisation. also
an amazing jazz improviser, toured with
Bobby McFaren for years and um so he
studied with her. So he's brought a
bunch of like vocal games which I think
is really a a blast. Um
and so that's kind of the stuff that he
brings. He invents them and brings that.
Um, and what's interesting is, um,
this is not exactly in the heart of the
work, but I am used to being in the
supporting role for Shaol.
And when Travis and I did our first
weekend, the weekend before, I fell down
the stairs that are right behind me
[laughter]
>> and I broke my wrist, my right wrist.
I'm right-handed.
>> And so he showed up. He was going to
come on Thursday. He came on Monday. I
fell on Saturday. He was in my house
Monday morning and stepped in and took
care of his auntie.
>> And I'm used to being the assistant
teacher for Shaol and I'm used to being
the caregiver because I took care of my
sweet mama for about 15 years. And so it
was suddenly this like, oh wow, here I
am. [laughter]
I'm now the lead teacher and I have a
broken wing. and I I let him take care
of me.
>> Wow.
>> Yeah, he's he's amazing.
>> Yeah, that must been a a spiritual
experience to say the least.
>> And then we while he was here, it was
the longest time we'd had just the two
of us. We had a whole week in my little
house here. And while he was here, we
worked up Jacob Collier's amazing song,
Little Blue. Are you familiar with that?
>> I'm familiar with Jacob Collier. I can't
remember the name.
>> Oh my god, his Little Blue song. So, we
borrowed a guitar from I play the piano.
I don't understand guitar, but we
borrowed a guitar from my friend Jason,
another Jason, and worked that song up
and sang it for the group and also at my
little unarian fellowship. And we would
we were practicing it and we'd just look
at each other and just go
the burst just hears because it is who
we are to each other.
>> Yeah.
>> Wow. Okay. Incredible. That's so
beautiful. Um All right. Well, let's
speak on the um
so I'm I'm a bit of a musician. I came
through it came through it through a
love of music. Um started as a DJ more
than anything and then of course I've
expanded into um more on the electronic
side of things, more on the beat making
side of things. Uh writing is my
favorite thing out of all of it. But
I've been lucky enough to be surrounded
by incredible talented musicians. Like
some of the most insane guitar players
are good friends of mine. I just feel so
lucky. Um, but I've been in these
moments where, you know, there's band
practice at at my place and I'm watching
these like just unifying moments of just
words being spoken without words and
just the prediction, just the jazz of
jamming, you know. Um, I'm sure you've
been a part of these in so many various
different ways. um whether it's you
leading like on your TED talks for
example you led the crowd in in singing
everybody in unison in those sort of um
you know again unifying experiences
what is that do you think I mean what
compared to our [laughter]
impossible question but
>> no it is it makes me I did that whole
second TED talk by the way there was
about a thousand people in that room
>> and I got them I did an experiment and I
didn't have a plan B if [snorts] they
didn't do it. I had them all got them
all started singing and then I I
abdicated leadership and they all
decided when it was over
>> and they did it. I and I'd never the
most I'd ever done it with is 300 people
and
that was triple that at least. So, um
but I did that second TED talk because I
can't get over what can happen in a
group of people.
>> Yeah.
>> And singing is the primary way that I've
been doing it. I'm a song leader. I have
been for years and years and all the
singing resistance stuff that's been
happening in the Twin Cities. Uh I
planted all those seeds for that
community over decades of community song
leading in that
place and now you know there's thousands
of people who show up and like sing and
march in the streets and and now it's a
worldwide movement. So what the hell? We
never know what we're doing.
>> Yeah. How cool. But [clears throat] I
started
when I was singing solo back in my 20s.
I started as a jazz singer.
>> And
there is such magic in that. Uh
uh and the the closest thing I can think
of is it's like the mycelial connections
between trees.
>> I love that.
>> Right. And human beings have it because
otherwise why would a thousand people
stop a song all at the same damn time?
And why would it happen over and over
and over again in groups of 30, 40, 50,
60, 80, 100, 300 people? It's like it
happens all the time when I'm leading in
this way. And it has to be without paper
because I think the paper makes us more
certain.
Like we're not I I actually I wrote a
little song called Listen with Your
Skin. It's a little community layer
song.
>> That's a good name.
>> Yeah. In five four time of course
because you know it had to be groovy.
But that is what I think happens when
we're in that place. You know I lead I
get it started and then I abdicate and
then people start like
okay it's up to us now. And I think that
kind of singing
lights up the my the thing that's
already there all the time, the mycelial
connections between us. And you know, I
did a lot of team building when I was a
consultant all those years. And it was
like I I could have just had them
singing together. And I used to I used
to get him singing rounds um as a way to
experience being an individual as part
of a group as part of a larger hole
>> because that's what a round is. You're
singing a part with a little group and
then everybody starts at different times
and it makes a hole.
>> And it's a perfect metaphor for how
complicated and rewarding it is to be
part of a
group of people doing something in the
world. Yeah. Yeah. Emphasis on both
complicating and rewarding. I that's
that's well said.
>> Um okay, I have to share this story. I
um it's happened a few times in my in my
you know DJ career. Uh more recently
within the last year um I essentially
was doing a DJ set at my friend's
private place. Um you did mention my
celial. I will just be honest. We there
was a little bit of mushrooms involved.
Some magic mushrooms were involved. But
um we everyone was basically say 30 to
40 people basically on a small dose of
of mushrooms. And um that time almost
more than ever of my like 14 years of
DJing. The the crowd the people there um
they were a lot of like it was like
meditation teachers and raiki healers
and very like spiritual people. Um they
were choosing the songs through me. I it
was this most out of body experience.
Um, I had some kind of mapped out, oh, I
want to play this song. I have this
playlist. I had kind of like a little
bit of a few hundred kind of gathered
that I wanted to to play with songwise.
Um, but by the end of it, I mean, I
mean, for at least probably 45 minutes,
they were choosing the songs. It was
this unifying experience. We actually
led up into um I play a lot of
electronic music. It was a lot of
ecstatic dancing, a lot of very um some
goofy stuff, some beautiful stuff. And
by the end of it, it's almost like
headbanging, like heavy stuff. And I
didn't plan to go there at all, but uh
elevated us up. We're all dancing.
Everyone's dancing. I played this song.
Um, funny enough, the lyrics were uh
like, I can give you what you want, what
you need. And that was that song. And
then I just felt intuitively that was
the peak. And I was like, that was it.
We've arrived. And I just slowly faded
the music down. And I got on the mic and
I was like, "Uh, hey guys, welcome back
to Earth." And then everyone just was
holding their head and like laughing
hysterically and everyone's like, "Where
did we just go?" And my friend's mom who
was inside, like she was kind of coming
out and dancing a little bit, but she
was like, "You guys just went on such an
adventure." But anyway, um, you know,
those unifying experiences, there was
really, [snorts] it has its silliness to
it, has its like, you know, oh, it's
fun. We're all dancing and we had a
little bit of mushrooms, but it was this
very profound, beautiful opening to
these unifying experiences. We even
before I even started playing, we all
did a guided meditation together. Um,
we set our intentions for what we wanted
to kind of experience that evening. Um,
it was just this wonderfully beautiful
thing. I'm sure we've had so many
traditions in the past who have had
similar situations with chanting and and
mantras and and these sorts of things,
but um
>> yeah, I just uh I I wanted to share that
with you. I I couldn't resist. Um I I
thought that you would you would think
that was pretty cool. I'm sure you've
had pretty similar experiences where you
as the leader were kind of being, you
know, pushed into corners by the crowd.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. And uh I have so many thoughts
right now. There's a collision in my
head.
One is that um strangely you know I'm I
mentioned I train people to to to carry
my work you know to either just present
the five elements framework and take
people through an experience and then a
deeper training around how do you like
use it in a coaching way over you know
time
there are a number of people who are
psychedelic facilitators who are showing
up to learn my work because
>> singing is such a part of a lot of those
traditions and it was Well, didn't see
that coming. Sure, why not? Um,
I often I know that songs are alive.
They are another form. We're just
vibrating stuff and so are they. And I
have had them
over and over again. A song will come
and whisper in my ear. And I'll be
teaching or I'll be leading and a song
will show up and be like, "What are you
doing here? And then I'll I trust it,
you know. I want to be a good I feel
like I want to be trustworthy to magic,
you know,
>> that [snorts] magic will find me. I will
respond. So I just um
honoring the lumines whenever possible.
And so
I'll start singing the song and somebody
will burst into tears and say, "Oh, that
was my mom's favorite song and she just
died." You know, it's just like what?
And so I do feel like becoming more uh
awake to
the the all the living,
all the living, the the invisible, the
unseen world, the songs, the characters,
the energies that want to move and in
the world. And it's quite incredible to
see what can happen.
>> Yeah. And now I still I'm back to jazz.
I left it for a long time. When I was
singing it, I was so nervous I couldn't
sing it at all. I did a little bit, but
now I'm like, woo. So in my little town
of 2,000 people at the bottom of the
hill where I live, there's a historic
auditorium. It was a vaudeville
auditorium built in 1916 that just got
beautifully refurbished by a couple
local guys. and my dear friend Marissa
Dodge in my town of 2,00 people,
brilliant songwriter, great pianist,
singer, soul sister. Uh, a lot of times
on Friday night, like tonight I'll be
going down, she's going to be singing
with a friend of hers is a blues singer.
A lot of times she's playing with her
friend Dan who's a guitarist. and I'll
just go down there, hang out with my
friends in the little lounge and sit in
and sing all these songs I used to sing
when I was in my 20s, you know, 40 years
ago.
>> Only now I can sing them. And that
improvisation,
there's nothing better, you know, than
you've got a structure, you know, to
hang on to.
>> My first piano player said, "Don't
listen to the piano. I will screw you
up. Listen to the bass and you'll always
know where you are. And I thought, well,
that's good advice for life, right?
What's the baseline? What's the
fundamental
values
that are guiding my story? That's what
I'm going to listen to. And then I'm
improvising over that. Um, I I haven't
had a W2 since 1991,
so I've been making it up for a really
long time.
>> That's great. You're improvising.
>> Improvising. Big improvisation.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Okay, great. Um, all right.
Let's get a maybe a little more sticky
for people who are listening. Is there
anything that you could suggest anybody
listening right now? Like what what
could they start with? Is there some
some humming, some vocal techniques,
some um things they could start their
everyday morning with? What do you got
to offer anyone listening?
>> Well, let's see.
Uh, I'm tra I'm debating. I I think I'm
going to suggest that they play with
sound through laughing. The five
elements. If I have to introduce the
five elements framework quickly, I can
do it laughing.
[laughter]
So you can laugh like a big hairy o
and that'll get your chest opened up.
[laughter]
We all know somebody who laughs like
this, you know, SLIGHTLY OBNOXIOUS.
>> [laughter]
>> AND THEN THE WATER. THAT was fire. Then
drunk Julia Child [laughter]
for metal.
Baby for air. So laughing is a great way
to just open up the different sounds. I
also just feel like um if people are
wanting to do something less ridiculous,
uh you can voice your yawns when
appropriate.
Whenever I get people in the earth
voice, they're like
yawning perpetually.
>> Oh yeah.
>> Um so that's a way to sort of open the
channel between the earth the um chest,
the body and the head.
And a really easy access point is
reading children's books out loud even
if you're not reading for any children.
Because basically like if take like the
Wizard of Oz, you've got fire was king
of the forest, you've got earth and pay
no attention to that man behind the
curtain fire. Um somewhere
over the rainbow Dorothy and at least in
the movie was water, the witch is metal
and Glenda the good witch is air. And
you can do that with so many stories. so
much mythology, Winnie the Pooh, uh Lord
of the Rings. Uh yeah. So, but
children's books often take us into a
speaking.
>> Yeah.
>> More more variety in how we speak.
>> That's such a that's such a great idea.
And I love the I I love just going
through the different tiers of of
laughter. I I think I'm going to try
that. I'm try I'm going to try to do
that in the mornings just to like wake
myself up to the different uh you know,
versions wanting to come out. [laughter]
Uh uh I've I've also been listening to
uh I'm I'm a pretty big Harry Potter
fan. I I really love the books. Um and
Jim Dale reads the audio books on
Audible
>> and oh man, he is so good. He's he's
such a great voice actor. Uh I really
enjoy I feel like he hits all of those
throughout the whole time very well.
whenever there's I mean these are just
human qualities
>> being grounded passionate caring
incisive and clear and inspirational
>> and uh I interviewed an old friend and
student of mine who has been carrying
the work uh to international audiences.
He he teaches teachers at international
schools and so people from all over the
world will be in the room and he will
present the five elements to them
because as teachers you need to be able
to read the room modulate
you know be more conscious of your voice
because it's one of the primary things
you have and I said did you ever
encounter any cultural like
nose and he's like I never no I never
So
>> yeah, I mean there have been exceptions.
When I was talking about air, I was in
Cincinnati, Ohio. Actually, I'm headed
back there again to do some work with a
friend. Um but um I was saying, "Oh,
this is how we talk to babies, you
know." And this large African-American
woman raised her hand and I said, "Does
this make sense?" And she's like, "Well,
in my community, we don't talk to
children like that. We use fire." I was
like, "Well, give me some of that." It's
like, "Hey, come on over here. Give me
some sugar." You know, [laughter] and I
was like, "Yeah, that was so great." So,
there have been a few exceptions over
the years, but by and large, these are
just ways we have of being human, and we
often change our voice unconsciously. I
mean, I hope we talk to our pets
differently than we talk to our boss or
a scary stranger,
>> right? Yeah. I I I can't help it. If I
see a dog, there's a dog voice coming
out. There's a version of me who really
loves dogs and I'm going to talk to him
like that. [laughter]
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And then I have to It's funny. I
just met one of my neighbors and they
have this little tiny dog and I was
meeting him, you know, he's another
grown man. I'm like, "Hey, how you
doing? I'm Jacob." You know, I'm shaking
his hand and then he has this little
cute dog
>> and I'm like, "Hi, hey Julie. Hi. How
are you?" And then I Oh, yeah. Stand up.
I'm talking to you again. [laughter]
The variations.
>> Yeah. when I'm teaching uh I was at a
corporate event um in Atlanta last year
and I was teaching this to a bunch of
leaders uh and I love giving this to
leaders and I you know some of my
students have been teaching people in
leadership programs at universities and
I would love to get this in every one of
those because
I mean everybody deserves to have a
voice and leaders voices have a bigger
impact in the world because they're
leaders and when it's going well it's
It's much better. It's amplified. And
when things are not going well, it's
also amplified. But um I I count when I
was teaching the air voice, I said,
"Okay, I'm going to count to five and I
want you to talk to your pets or your
young ones in your life." So I count her
to three. And the whole room was just
like
And then everybody laughed, you know,
just like [laughter]
it's universal.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. We can't help it. Um
>> Okay. Uh you you mentioned a term in a
podcast I was listening to you that I
would like to explore more of code
switching. How our voice um based off of
like who we're interacting with um in
different environments. We all have it a
bit naturally, but can you expand more
and maybe even maybe give your
explanation or definition of what code
switching means for someone who's never
heard that before?
>> Yeah, I learned it from my friends uh
who are I learned it from
African-American friends. It's a term
that I heard
the muse just to say that when I'm
talking to my friends who are black, I
sound different than when I'm talking to
white people and or others. So, uh
I pay attention to those kinds of shifts
in my own world, but also in the worlds
of my students. So, I didn't originate
that, but I feel like it it can import
into how we're all code switching. We're
all shifting
uh depending on who we're talking to.
But then there's also a lot of
unconscious things we're doing with our
voices that are spilling all kinds of
information about us.
So,
uh, we're revealing our level of
education, uh, maybe our gender, maybe
our class, our mood, uh, our level of
health. You know, I I can always tell
when my favorite NPR people have a cold
in our podcast house. You know, they
have that kind of stuffy sound. Um, and
the people we know well, we can hear.
You know, when I was taking care of my
sweet mama, I could tell by the low of
hello when she answered the phone if it
was a good day or a bad day.
>> And we've all, I'm sure, all had that
experience where we call someone we know
well and they answer the phone and we
say, "What's wrong?"
You know, can hear it in the voice.
>> So, some of it is um we're we're
constantly shifting unconscious
unconsciously. And I think of code
switching as being something that's more
purposeful.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. And and would you um I don't want
to put words in your mouth by phrasing
it like this, but would you cons you
wouldn't consider it a bad thing though?
It's just something we kind of all do to
some to some degree. We're not trying to
like put on some sort of false mask.
We're trying to cuz I I feel like when
when I catch myself doing it, it's it's
just me trying to connect with someone
in a different way. It's just me trying
to maybe like meet meet where maybe I at
least in that moment perceive that
they're at. um trying to just lessen the
chances of miscommunication basically
trying to get right to the point and and
speak their language. Um I for me it
feels I'm coming from a good place but
I'm not sure if it's always perceived
that way.
>> Well, you know, you can use anything for
good or ill.
>> You know, uh Hitler had a great fire
voice.
>> Right.
>> Right. So, I think one of the things I
do hear from [clears throat] people is
like, "Well, this just doesn't feel
authentic to me."
>> Like, my air voice did not feel
authentic at all. Felt like putting the
cat in the bathtub. It's like I hate
that. So to me, being able to shift
is a good thing because we're
communicating across so many
differences, you know, generations,
cultures,
um, class, uh, I mean, all kinds of
things. And so,
uh, one of my mentors, Peter Block,
who's a leadership author, wrote really
beautiful books about community, um, as
well as leadership. And he says,
"Nothing happens in this world until
we're until we connect.
>> Nothing can happen between people." And
so
>> what I like to teach is is to have a big
enough sense of who you are as a person
and as a voice that if fire is like, you
know, making people kind of back off and
they're like, "H, that's a you can, you
know, if you're reading the room, you
can kind of tell it's like, oh, they're
backing away from me." you might be able
to switch to water and talk in a way
that is, you know, you're looking for
the connection,
>> right? Yeah.
>> And for a lot of women, water is like
how we're supposed to be. We're here to
take care of everyone all the time and
not be a and not be an
and, you know, have to be nice and it's
like, oh god. So, a lot of powerful
women have said, I can't afford to be in
that voice ever. And it's like, well,
you might not be able to be in that
voice at work, but you definitely need
to have your heart with you. And the
water is the voice of the heart. So, if
you have can get a big enough sense of
who you are,
um, you can come from all these
different places and still feel like
yourself,
>> right?
>> Yeah. [clears throat] I love that. What
some great points. I love the way you
said that. Uh it I I'm reminded of um
kind of my different variations at work
of even myself when I was younger. Uh I
worked at like clothing shops, at skate
shops, you know, and
>> the way I speak, not only my language,
but even my vocal tonality is going to
be different when it's, you know, a
16-year-old kid who's coming with like
$5 to get a new piece of grip tape on
his skateboard versus his grandma comes
with him. You know what I mean? So, I'm
just I'm going to speak to them a little
bit differently to try to to to meet
with them. But the the end goal is to
connect, you know. Um I I find
>> I find and I wonder what you think about
this. I uh
I hate to make generalizations of like a
whole generation, but I do find a lot
more younger people just say they say
less. Um they they speak less. I notice
it. And uh because I grew up working at
clothing stores, when I walk into
clothing stores, I'm always I want to be
greeted. I I want um I want them to say
hello. I don't really care about exactly
what they're saying. Hey, let me know if
I could help you with anything. Hey, we
have a special going on. Whatever it is,
I find more and more they just don't
speak much at all. Um,
>> have you noticed that? And, uh, if there
is anybody listening who maybe that is
their default state,
>> would you have any advice for them? Uh,
maybe they're afraid to speak, maybe
they're afraid of of what exactly
they're saying? Um, I don't know. Does
anything come to mind when I when I
mention that?
>> Yeah. What I I haven't noticed that
necessarily, but I have noticed the
vocal fry. You know, there's a lot of
younger people who are like talking,
you know, with a vocal fry,
>> which drives me nuts because it's
basically
>> anorexic. It's an anorexic tone. It's
like you're starving your vocal cords
for the air they need to function as
they were designed. Uh,
and then you're also not breathing as
much, so you're dumber.
>> [laughter]
>> You know what I mean? You're not you're
not spending air, you're not taking it
in, you're not giving it out. So, it's
this kind of frozen uh fry thing.
>> Um
what I have noticed is
the appetite for singing among
the younger generation. I mean, so many
of the people who are out in the streets
in Minneapolis, yeah, they're a bunch of
boomers and Gen Xers, too. But a lot of
the leaders in that are in their 30s and
40s. And
there's a whole movement. I know there's
people, I think, in Austin who do this
kind of singing. Um, where it's oral
tradition, no music, no performance,
it's just singing in the old way. And,
uh, there's certainly a lot going on now
with this whole singing resistance
movement. There's pods popping up
everywhere.
And a lot of the people who are showing
up at these singing camps where a lot of
this started are younger and they're
writing amazing songs. And so what's
interesting is it feels like there's a
bifurcation. There's like the people who
only communicate through text and gaming
and sort of being silent. Yeah. Meetings
through portals. Technology portals. Uh,
and then there's a whole subculture
that's probably a lot of the people that
were at your dance, your rave, you know,
who are looking for these more organic
ancient ways of being together with
dance ecstatic.
Um, there's a great book actually that
talks about this. I want to get it in
the get it in. I thought of it earlier
when you were talking about your thing
>> uh that you did. Um,
it's called Dancing in the Streets. A
history of collective ecstasy by Barbara
Erin Reich. And it's not a new book, but
I think about it a lot. I referenced it
in both of my books because I think we
used to do this all the time. We need
it. We need a break from the ego. We're
not supposed to be alone in here. It's
bad for us, right? Don't leave me alone
with this woman, you know? And so her
her whole hypothesis and she she builds
it all up is that for most of human
history we had regular opportunities to
lose ourselves
>> usually through some sort of chemical
alteration, special food, dance, music,
trance. Um, and we did it all the time.
And so we're wired that way. And just
usually with that, she tracks it back to
the rise of the Catholic Church when
those festivals kind of were suppressed.
Uh, then the word melancholy,
melancholas shows up and we start
getting depressed because we're not
supposed to be alone. And that just
helps me so much. It's not it's not just
like go to therapy because you're
lonely. It's like no actually you're
just a human being who's not getting
like fundamental experiences that human
beings need to get a break from their
ego. And so I'm really celebrating the
rise of these kinds of events that you
talked about in trans dance, ecstatic
dance, um singing camp, um these
opportunities. You can't deny that
you're connected to other human beings
when you're in a group of 75 people and
they all stop singing at the same
moment.
>> Yeah.
>> You cannot
mind your way out of that.
>> Right.
>> Right. That happened and it happened. We
all shared it. We felt it in our bodies.
It's undeniable that we are deeply
connected to each other.
Yeah.
>> So, I think people are I think the human
spirit is always looking for that. Where
is that community? Um
>> Yeah. Yeah. I I agree. And I think we
should all lean into lean into finding
something that makes sense to us. I've
even done it's been a few years now that
I think of it, but um I've even done I
would go to like a you know just a
nightly guided meditation where some guy
would would talk for a little while and
then he'd kind of talk about meditation
and then we'd ask questions and those
sorts of things. But they would always
start with chanting. Um I forget exactly
what chant they did.
>> I don't think it was like the Hari
Krishna, but it was some some sort of
Buddhist related chant of some sort. And
um I remember when I first did it cuz I
didn't know any of these people or
whatever. And it was kind of in a small
room. It was like in someone's living
room. And uh the first few minutes I was
like this feels weird. And I was really
aware of my own voice and everything.
And then after a few I feel totally
opened up and now I'm part of this
unifying thing. And then I was way freer
to ask questions that came up and and I
felt connected to these people that I
really didn't even have an opportunity
to, you know, I'd introduce myself to
them and say hello, but I didn't know
these people, but I felt vastly more
connected to them after just chanting
for like 10 minutes.
>> I know it it's so simple and I people
are so scared of it. I mean, if I if I
had a nickel for every time somebody
said, "Are we gonna hold hands and sing
kumbaya?" And my friend Melanie Deorg
gets all up in people's faces because
Kumbaya is a sacred
song in the African-American tradition.
And she's African-American song leader,
singer, conductor, composer, and she's
like earth voice, total earth voice. But
um my friend Peter Block, I'll be going
to Cincinnati. He he's written really
beautiful books. One is called
Community, a structure for Belonging. He
wrote one with his friend John Mcnite
called Abundant Community. And it's just
about what are the sort of conversations
you can have in a group of people so
that the future is distinct from the
past. And he and I have chased around a
lot together um co- keynoting.
and
um he helped
give words to what I instinctively felt
music did in a room. And so I'll be
going to Cincinnati in in early May to
bring music to a gathering um about
community that he's part of and a lot of
other people. Um,
and singing is going to be a part of it.
And I'm so grateful that he actually
gave a name to what I intuitively felt
the music was doing. One of the things
he says is, you know, the thing about
he's kind he's tall sardonic Jewish guy,
very funny, and he's like, you know, the
thing about music is even if you hate
it, it's got you. You can't defend
against it. I was like,
>> "Yeah." So, we would do keynotes, you
know, at these big conferences and he
would we'd both come on stage
>> and I would before anybody said anything
after the introduction, I would do a
song and people would all be just like,
you know, this is at like a big hotel
conference room and this is not what's
expected. The piano, I have a key big
keyboard up there and even they walk in
the room and the piano hasn't like
>> Yeah.
>> looking at their little thing, you know?
I was like, "Am I am I in the right
room?" And then I would do a song and he
would get up and, you know, because he's
a an old white man with a strong
handshake and a bunch of best-selling
books, he would just name what just
happened and what my role was. And our
dance was that it was like jazz. He
would talk and then I'd hear something
he'd say and then I'd just go stand at
my keyboard and he would bring his
comments in for a landing and then I
would do a song and people said, "Did
you write that song just for that?" It
was like, "No, actually I had did write
a lot of songs based on things he said
because he's so eloquent." But we were
plugged into the same kind of I don't
know meaning
>> Yeah.
>> vein. And so we would do that back and
forth. It was such a joy. Just so I'm
excited I get to do this again. But
>> yeah, that's so exciting. Yeah, you're
speaking through the myelial network of
of one another. Um
>> exactly. Exactly.
>> Yeah. Okay. So, um I would like to talk
about your books briefly. Um your first
book, how long has it been since you've
written that one?
>> Uh 2011, I think. Yeah, it's been a
minute. It's full voice, the art and
practice of vocal presence. And it goes
through the five elements. Basically, it
opens up a big conversation about what
voice is, you know, beyond what we
normally think. And then I got asked to
write a second book and this is that
both of them are are on audio book and
ebook and all the things.
>> Oh yeah.
>> But then I got asked to write vocal
intelligence, leading with vitality,
presence, and impact. And so this one
still is about the five elements, but
it's kind of aimed more at leaders um
leadership. And so I tell a lot of
stories about leaders. Um this the
second one though started as an audio
book. So I really recommend the audio
book for vocal intelligence especially
because it also includes about an hour
of my music
>> that I
>> would you know put and then there's also
a part in there at the end. It's called
who you going to be while you do what
you do. And it's basically a keynote
that I do a lot. It's a musical keynote.
um, five ideas for sustaining energy and
humanity in the midst of chaos. And so I
took that keynote and I made it into,
you know, put it at the end of the book.
Um, and it there's five ideas and five
songs and stories and things. So those
are my books.
>> Yeah. Wonderful. Okay.
>> I just got the paperback of Vocal
Intelligence yesterday.
>> Oh, nice. That probably feels great to
like actually hold the paperback in your
hand. That must be cool. Yeah.
>> I never planned it.
Yeah. Yeah. Did you plan on even writing
a first book? Like is that something you
had on your agenda before you?
>> You know, my strategic plan has been
what the hell? [laughter]
>> Yes.
>> You know, so friend,
>> a woman heard me in Georgia when I was
there presenting to a group uh and she
connected to my first publisher, Barrett
Kohler, great publisher, and said, "I
just heard this woman and I think she
should write for us." So I came home
from that trip with an email from an
editor and I was like I had to read it
four times. It was like what you know I
make I've made nine recordings. I write
songs and record songs. I'm a singer
songwriter. That's what I make. I love
to write too but um it didn't hurt that
these two pe mentors of mine Peter Black
and Margaret Wheatley are like rockstar
authors for them and they gave a really
nice endorsement as well. So So, didn't
see that coming, but I put it put I
actually had an ecstatic experience when
in the rewrite. I don't remember much
about it. I just remember sitting at my
dining room table
>> just in an ecstatic state rewriting this
book. And uh and then I got approached
for the second one last year. I had no
idea. Um I actually ignored the first
email [laughter]
from this agent. I get [clears throat]
all kinds of like everybody I get all
kinds of silly things but
>> yeah like this is probably AI and
probably not not a real person.
>> Exactly.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Uh okay so what have you I mean
the answer may be very well your second
book or in your second book but
what has changed about your message
since your first book if anything?
>> That's a great question.
You know, I feel like I just I'm just
more sure that it's valuable.
>> Do you know? I've seen it's been a long
I mean, I've seen a lot since I wrote
the first one and I had already done a
lot of work. Um,
as I tell the people I'm training, you
can really trust the work.
>> You know, you can trust these elements.
You can trust the voice. You can trust
the soul of the people you're working
with. Um, so I think the the biggest
thing that's changed is my conviction
that this is an essential part of being
human. Um, part of my work, part of my
service work is I have a comfort choir.
We sing for people who are in hospital
or hospice.
>> You call us up for no and we'll show up
four or five people for no money and
just sing for you songs of comfort and
healing. It's the best work I do. And so
I've had a lot of exposure to death and
dying through that work, but also I've
just had a lot of people die in my life
and um lots of them rather consciously
and generously sharing their
experience. And so for me,
I think voice is just a huge part of how
we get our gifts in this world before we
die. I think we come here loaded with
something.
And I think our job while we're here is
to learn to love and be loved. To quote
the old Nature Boy song, the greatest
thing you'll ever learn is just to love
and be loved in return.
>> And to give the gifts that you're loaded
with and the voice is is huge part of
both of those things. So,
um,
>> so I feel like as I'm as I'm getting
closer to my own departure, hopefully
it'll still Well, I who knows who knows,
but I am more convinced that
uh voice is a really big part of being
having a good life.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Being able to uh communicate
what's really in you, kind of being a a
conduit. I wrote this line the other day
that was uh something along the lines of
uh uh I am a a human a human-shaped hole
in the universe.
It was something like that, you
[laughter] know.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I thought it was kind of
good. Um
>> really good. Yeah.
But yeah, I I think it is so many of
these things. Uh call them spiritual if
you'd like, but you know, it's just a
matter of like we said, trying to get
out of our own way, trying to unccork
the ego and just allow um you know,
something that
is more divine or more true or uh is in
communion with one another to to come
forth, you know,
>> to to really pour out,
>> right? What else would you rather be
doing with your time?
>> I [laughter] know, right?
>> Really? You know?
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. Um, okay. Uh, I just want to
glance over my notes here. Uh, we are
getting up here in time, but I think I
had a couple more. Um,
oh, okay. Uh, I did want to ask you
about, um, so, uh, I'm I'm a big fan of
meditation and, uh, one that I found
that I keep coming back to kind of my
daily for for a few the last few years
has been actually transcendental
meditation. It's a mantra meditation,
TM. if you're familiar. Um, and uh, it's
for me, I've just basically I was given
a nonsense word. It doesn't have meaning
to anybody but me. Um, it's just kind of
a trigger word that in my head I know
it's just a relaxation of my nervous
system. And I repeat that for 20
minutes, ideally twice a day if I can
get it, but definitely once a day for 20
minutes. Um, and I notice especially
after like the the couple hours
afterwards, uh, it's almost like the
background of the mantra is continually
going on like even after I stand up and
that's almost where kind of the peace
is. It's like this I've cleared away
some of the the mud of the the daily
self and I have this continuous like
calm reminder that everything is okay
and my nervous system is fine and I can
allow it all, etc., etc. It just kind of
works in the background. Um, something I
noticed on your on uh your TED talks was
like I would be listening to my phone
was on the counter and after everyone
was done singing, you'd be talking and
then I think like you would start the
mantra back up or you'd have the
audience start it back up and I would
pick back up right with them. So like
even in my apartment or even in my house
here, I was like the mantra of the group
singing that I had just listened to was
still working through me and I don't
even I didn't really consciously notice
it until it was picked back up. So, um,
I I guess I want to kind of ask you
about what do you think about mantras
and do you think singing, especially
group singing, is a bit of a mantra that
kind of stays with us? Is it like a
deposit into a bank that that just
keeps, you know, gaining in in currency,
I guess?
>> Yes. Yeah. I
I always have something in my going in
my background. I people give me music
all the time and I'm like I just don't
listen to it because I have an inner I
have an inner Spotify going all the time
and it's usually something I'm working
on, you know, I'm I've you know I'm
almost always writing something and
so
but I've also noticed that
the [clears throat] silence after the
song
or the chant
is maybe that's why we do it. So after
years of of noticing this, I made a
little poem and it's the first time I've
written a poem that I didn't write it
down until I got it done. I did it all
oral tradition and I was I lead retreats
and a singing retreat for women in
Mexico. And yes, it's fun. Um and I was
walking the beach and writing this. I
remember kind of where I was and it goes
like this. We make the song for the
silence that comes after
and laughter's for the ache that lingers
in our middle
and the riddles for what happens as we
quest for the rhyme and time is for the
knowing of the timeless.
And I'm less inclined to think that I
make a song. It's clear. It's been here
all along.
And my longing and this silence calls
the song.
>> That's so good.
>> Thank you. [laughter]
>> I love that one.
>> Yeah. So I feel like there's sound all
the time everywhere. And then when we
use our voices in some way, we plug into
the resonant hum of life
that is happening all the time. And then
I do think sometimes the song is just
the little factory for the byproduct of
that resonant
wholesome silence afterwards.
>> Yeah. Wow. So well said. I feel like you
answer my question better than I could
have even dreamed of. That's so good. Um
yeah.
>> Yeah. It Yeah. digs us out of our own
way. Uh okay. Um well great. Um we are
getting up here. Barbara, thank you so
much for your time. Um can I just ask
you anybody who's listening who wants to
explore more um of course they can go
check out your books. Those will be
linked down below. I'll link your
website down below. But what are you
working on? What do you got going on in
the next um coming months or years? What
can we look forward to as far as your
work?
>> Oh my gosh. Well, the things I know
about, you know, there are things that
always emerge that I was like, "Oh,
didn't see that coming. What the hell?"
>> Um, I have regular online full voice
fundamentals courses that I do fiveweek
introduction to the elements. So, if
people are interested in digging into
those, I do them a couple times a year
and it's a blast. Um, so that's a really
easy access. Um, I'm also creating a
self-directed course in the next couple
months if people want to be able to just
do it themselves. Um, I think it's more
fun with other humans, but you know. Uh,
and then I also am leading some retreats
uh about living and dying. I made a new
retreat called living dying music and
mystery. And it is a mix of telling
stories from what I've learned from my
friends who have died from friends and
family members. Uh
it's kind of like an extended death
cafe, you know, with exploring questions
around death and dying. And then a lot
of singing so that
you're loaded up with some songs that
you can take to the people around you or
andor yourself as you look at your own
mortality. And um so I do doing that in
Pennsylvania in the fall and in on
Whedby Island also in the fall and in
Bayfield, Wisconsin next winter. So
yeah, that's the growing edge of my
work. I just started that in the last
couple years and it's been really really
rich.
>> Oh yeah, I I I can only imagine. I
listen to a lot of Ramdos. I'm a big fan
of Ramdos. Um, and he talks I I learned
so much from him when he talks about uh
working with people who are dying. Uh,
even even him just talking about taking
care of his own father and his
stepmother as they were um, you know,
uh, leaving leaving Earth and Yeah. Wow.
What a beautiful endeavor. What a truly
uh, human experience.
>> Yeah. I'll also be doing some work in
California this fall um around voice and
or living and dying. We're still
organizing the tour u probably around
Monterey Carmel area and San Diego. So,
>> okay. And they can follow you.
>> The easiest way is just to get on my
website and
sign up for my stuff and then you'll get
you'll get some songs as they get born
and um some other news about what's
what's shaken.
>> Very well. Yeah. So, everybody head to
the website. All that's linked down
below. So, um, do you stay active on any
social media, any Facebook, Instagram,
anything like that? Or
>> Facebook, Instagram, and I I'm also on
LinkedIn, but I'm less interested. But,
>> yeah, LinkedIn's a weird one, isn't it?
>> It is. Just strange. Yeah. I just don't
I don't know. And in I'm still new
enough to Instagram, but I'm getting
better. I'm getting better at it. Um,
I'm a cold plunger. I I It's March, you
know, I got in in this year in March
>> 22nd, uh, the river was open. So,
>> oh, the river, too.
>> Very cold river.
>> So, uh, yeah, I write I often post from
down there, record things when I've just
gotten out and I'm like, woo.
>> That's [laughter] Yeah, that's that's a
high followed by a silence unlike unlike
no other. The um I feel like the sound
of less inflammation in your body, it
brings out such a clarity of mind.
>> I just absolutely love the feeling.
Yeah. And I miss it in the deep winter
because I can't get in. Yeah. Yeah. I'm
actually thinking I got this my back
door there. I'm thinking I'm going to uh
invest one of those uh chillers now that
I have my own home. I can uh uh do a
cold plunge at home. So, I'm with you on
the cold plunge.
>> All right.
>> Yeah.
>> You might be.
>> Yeah, I'm a cold punch guy, too. Uh all
right, Barbara. Well, thank you again um
so much for your time. Uh thank you so
much for your wisdom. Thank you just for
doing your work and and following your
intuition. Um it seems you've helped
many people. Uh it was it was great to
hear from you and explore more of your
work. I'm looking forward to checking
out more of your work in the future and
uh this was such a great time with you.
So, just thank you so much.
>> Thank you so much. It was a real joy to
to chat with you and I hope what we came
up with was useful to other people. But
honestly, I had a ball.
>> That's what I'm
>> It's a win already for me.
>> I I I feel a little selfish sometimes of
like I just love doing this. I just
really get excited to have these
conversations. So, I guess I'll hit
record, you know? So,
like I don't know if it's going to do
anything in the world, but my job is to
make sure people know about what I
carry. That's all I want is to be
useful. So,
>> yeah. Yeah. Well, I think you're
accomplishing that. And um yeah, anybody
who's listening, check out more of
Barbara's work. Uh follow her, reach out
to her if you have any more questions.
Um and then what do I always say at the
end of these episodes? If you haven't
drank any water today, what are you
doing, man? You got to drink some water.
And if you haven't stretched today, do a
little stretching. And then how about
you do a little singing as well? Test
out your five elements and uh test out
your singing [music] voice. Uh Barbara,
thanks one more time. Listeners, love
yourself and we will see you next
[music] episode. Hello and welcome to
the Junkyard Love.
>> Hey, everything's going to be all right.
>> It's all good. It's all good.
>> The Junkyard Love podcast. [music]
[music]
Five. Four. Three. The junkyard. Two.